And this side welcome back to the
channel. So till now we have covered the
refresh scope and how we can do dynamic
refresh but we end that topic like this
question. Let's say that this is
something which we have already covered.
Okay. And in the config server we have
invoke/actuator/refresh
and we have hundred of microservices
which are fetching the properties from
the config server. So our question was
do I have to invoke actuator/refresh
for all of these 100 of microservices.
So currently
answer is yes like whatever the approach
we were using. So we were using
actuator/refresh
way right. So we were calling this API
okay over the config servers and we have
to invoke this endpoint at all
microservices
then only our dynamic refresh will work
and also we have ended that this can be
resolved through spring cloud bus and
that's where we are okay so let's first
see before even jump to spring cloud bus
let's first see how event is published
within one application itself. So we are
not talking about multiple
microservices, distributed microservices
within one application how you publish
an event and how it internally works
because these things are highly related.
So see this
I created one event my custom event.
This is something which I want to
publish to listeners. Okay. So let's
understand this. I have a publisher
and I have listeners.
Listener one, listener two and so many
listeners.
So this my custom event is something
which I want to publish to the listener.
So a payload will go let's say and that
payload is my custom event. Okay. So
this payload will go. So you can say
that this is my message which I want to
send and it should extend application
event interface. So here when we do
publish event write this publish event
accept the type of this class
application event interface.
So that's why whatever the message you
have to create it has to extend this.
And here this is a simple constructor
where we have to provide the source.
This source is nothing but a information
about who is publishing. So here let's
say
this is the publisher this publisher
details. So you can say that this is my
source. So here I am passing this
object. So all the information about
this publisher that's all. Okay. And the
messages whatever the message we want to
publish. So this could be like more
fields which you want. So here currently
I have only one field which I want to
publish into my payload. So that's why I
have only message but you can have more
and this is just a getter. So this is
very very simple class of a event
message which I want to publish.
Now I have one
bean of let's say that my event
publisher. So this is the publisher
which is going to publish it. Okay. So I
am using this application event
publisher. So this is already present
into the spring framework. It is an
interface you can say that which
abstract the logic of publishing an
event like it's not uh there are lot of
things involved when publishing an
event. So all those things are
abstracted to us. All we have to do is
we have to invoke this method publish
event. That's all I will tell you
internally what it does. Okay. But for
now consider this. This is the interface
which makes our job easy. We we just
have to invoke publish event. That's
all. And we just have to pass our
payload or you can say that event which
we have to publish.
So that's why I have autowired this
publisher object application event
publisher and this is my publish method.
Internally I am using this publisher
object and I'm calling just publish
event and
this is my
event or message my custom event. So I'm
creating a new object my custom event
source is like who is publishing. So
this is the uh publisher right? So
source about this and the message which
I want to publish. Okay. So this is the
simple publishing logic I have. So this
is done. Now here listeners we can have
so many listeners. So I am just creating
one listener. So here if you see this is
just a bean like my event listener
annotated with at the rate component. So
here I have put created one listener add
the rate event listener and which event
it is handling any method name you can
give. So I am handling my custom event.
So this is listening to this.
So similarly we can have different
listener listening to different
different events. Okay. So let's say
event two. So the listener three might
be listening to this event two
something. But this event which I am
creating it is listening to my custom
event this one.
And once the event is received this is
just an object right? So you can just
access whatever you want to access.
Okay. So here I'm doing event.get get
message and so that this message I can
get.
Okay. So here very important thing is
that this is the very very minimalistic
code you required to test how event is
published within one application. How it
will work internally I will tell you. So
okay. So here I am just adding a normal
controller just to test the flow. So
here uh I autowired this publisher. This
is the publisher right? So I have now
its object here.
Okay. And using this object I am
invoking its publish message. This
publish message method I am invoking so
that uh this get invoked. So this is
just to test the flow. And now from
postman I am just invoking this endpoint
within app publish. So this endpoint I
invoke I pass the message hello world.
Now what it will do? It will invoke our
publisher publish method. So this one.
So it invoked this method and pass the
message hello world. Now it is doing
publisher.publish event. It creates a
new object and pass this. So here if you
see the output it says received event
message hello world. So this is we have
printed here receive event message hello
world. So even though we have invoked
this from the controller, it just
published an event. It hasn't invoked
this directly. So internally it is able
to find this listener and invoking it
properly.
So how's it working?
See this it is very important to
understand that one.
So in the publisher, so we have a
publisher.
So we have multiple listener.
Okay. So here this was our publisher and
there we were publishing an event. So
internally it goes to one of the helper
class. So see it internally goes to this
class simple application event
multiccaster on Java. So this is the
framework code. You can uh dig deeper
into it. You can put a debugger point
and see how it is working. So you will
encounter this code what it will do it
is see it is iterating
it is iterating over a list of listeners
okay so here what I'll tell you that
when we create a listener like this and
when you start an application
internally it creates a list like this
okay my custom event this is the event
who is listening. So my event listener
is listening. Listener one, listener
two, listener three. So for each event
it has a list of listeners who are
listening. Okay. So it has complete
detail about it. All which method need
to be invoked. Okay. What all the
parameters is required like all the
details. So it stores certain
information that okay for this event
what are all the listeners I have to
pass the or publish the event.
So it is iterating over the list and
what list based on the type. So event
type what whatever the event we have its
type we have. So based on that it will
get a list of all the listeners of it
and then it is invoking that listener.
So here if you see this is all the
information you will get about a
listener. So let's say the type is my
custom event. This is the message type
right? This is the message type here.
So I want to see that hey who is
listening to this event because we are
we have published this event in publish
event we have published this my custom
event. So I need to check who is
listening to this event.
So I am taking out a list based on that
give me all the listener who are
listening to my custom event. So you get
this kind of information here. I'm
zooming it. Hey what's the bean name?
what's the method name I have to invoke
okay so full details all the it has all
the target method method keys everything
okay about if there are let's say 100
listener it have all 100 listener
information about it
okay and one by one it is invoking this
listener
so one thing you got to know that this
is the flow when you invoke a publish
and pass an event it internally goes to
this multiccaster
which iterate over this list of
listeners which it take out based on
this event and invoke the method one by
one. So it is very similar to observer
design pattern in LLD
and it's all happening in the sync
manner within an application within one
application this is the flow
but now we are talking about distributed
microservices
okay microservices one which is act as a
publisher now it has to
broadcast an event to multiple
microservices which are act as let's say
listeners or consumers
Now they are not within one application.
So how it will work? That's where
spring cloud bus comes into the picture.
But again
whatever we have understood about one
application that info or you can say
that that logic is still there even in
the spring cloud bus. How? So see this
understand with this flow. Now let's say
this is microser A which is currently
acting as a publisher.
It published an event.
Now this event earlier it was
what
your where is our event? Yeah. So
earlier it was application event.
Whatever the my custom event it extend
application event. Now here whatever the
event we will pass here. Whatever the
event we will pass that would be a
subclass of remote
application event. Remote application
event means it is not within a same
class of same application. This event
has to go to a remote destination
somewhere.
So using that our spring cloud was
intercepted.
Once spring cloud was intercepted it
make use of our message broker
infrastructure. So our message broker
let's say rabbit MQ or Kafka that should
be present up and running. Okay. And
whatever the logic whatever the
configuration we have it's totally like
should be present. Spring cloud bus only
use it. It do not manage it. It only use
it to send the message.
So spring cloud bus intercept your event
serialize it. put it into JSON form and
use your message broker and send the
message. So internally it create let's
say you are using rabbit MQ internally
it will create a que it will create an
exchange and then it will bind it with a
routing key it will do everything which
is abstracted to us we don't even know
okay only thing is we have to grant
access to the spring cloud bus hey this
is the message broker you can use
internally if let's say if you have
Kafka it will take care of creating the
topic inside it will take care of
creating the partition ation everything
so everything is abstracted to us we are
not going to manage the message broker
very important I'm saying you we are not
managing message broker with spin cloud
bus okay so what's the retry mechanism
how you handle the failure what are the
offset handling nothing is managed by
spin cloud bus it is just a layer which
is used to just send a message and it
make use of message broker now message
broker again pass it to the spring cloud
bus which is in another application. Now
it des serialize it. D serialize it
means JSON to Java object and it pass to
simple application event multiccaster.
So the same thing is happening but here
if you see this publish event is present
into one application now ultimately is
reached to simple application event
multiccaster into different application
and from there it broadcast to the event
listeners. So this is happening like it
is publish event is coming from a same
application. Simple application
multiccaster like
okay I am getting an event maybe it is
from the same application but internally
splink crowd bus abstracted all the
info. So from which micros service how
message broker is used, how it is uh you
can say that listening to the queue or
topic fetching it and it only pass
serialize it and then pass it to the
simple application event multiccaster.
So this flow is clear. So even though
spring cloud was we are using we had to
understand how in one application it is
working that will give us better
clarity.
So spring cloud bus abstract all the
details regarding message broker. If you
are using rabbit QMQ we don't have to
create exchange. We don't have to create
Q. We don't have to bind the Q and
exchange using routing key. Everything
is decided by spring cloud bus.
Similarly if you are using Kafka we
don't have to create topics. We don't
have to create partition. We don't have
to manage offsets etc. So it's all
abstracted to us. And that's why very
important again I am repeating spring
cloud buzz is just a wrapper above the
message broker
do not use it for critical message
where you need full control over topic
creations retry mechanism message
persistence acknowledge if you have all
this requirement don't use spring cloud
bus only use spring cloud bus which for
low volume non-critical messages like
refreshing the config clear the cache
which is you can say that even if it got
delayed
or uh if it doesn't success and next
time you refresh or next time you clear
the cache it should work fine. So less
critical and low volume traffic you
should use spring cloud bus. It is not
recommended for critical high volume
system because it do not give us a way
to control our message broker. So
wherever our message broker is, it's
just a layer above it just uses it and
pass the message and internally it just
creates some temporary queue exchange
whatever it does we don't know it all
abstracted to us.
Okay. So understood in what use case you
have to use and in what use case
scenarios we don't have to use spring
cloud bus.
So let's do
this
producer
and you can say that listener or
consumer in different different microser
now they are not in same application. So
lot do a setup. So one thing you know
that when they are in different
different microser you need a message
broker. So for testing we have to set up
a some message broker. So for now I am
using rabbit MQ. So if you have Mac you
can use this command to install the
rabbit MQ. If you don't have and you can
it's very easy to install and start
whether it's Windows and Mac OS. So very
simple I just installed the Rabbit MQ
and using this command I started it. So
over this local host and this port you
see that rabbit MQ is started username
password default is guest guest.
So my message broker is started. So
first first setup is done.
Now second setup is publisher. So now I
am setting the publisher. So in the
pom.xml
we have to add this dependency. We have
to tell what message booker I am using.
So currently rabbit MQ is the is
following the AMQ protocol. Okay, AMQP
protocol and uh so that's why I have
added this dependency. If you are using
Kafka then you can double check it's uh
spring cloud starter bus Kafka is the
dependency you need. Double check it.
Okay. So first thing is we have to have
a dependency in the publisher.
Second is here
whatever the message broker you have to
provide an access. So
host port number username password.
Okay. So this I provided so that my
producer is able to connect to the
message broker.
Again this is just for testing. That's
why I have username password here.
Otherwise never put your secret or
credentials in application.properties
like this. It should always be keep safe
in some uh secret manager or it will be
passed to an environment variable. So
this is just for testing.
Okay. I have an application name let's
say producer service running on port
number 8081. And this is one very
important where most of the engineer who
are working with spring cloud was faces
the problem.
Each producer or you can say that each
application
which is making use of this is message
broker it which is making use of a
spring cloud bus spring cloud bus
it is granted one unique ID or you can
say that bus ID
okay why it is important now understand
with this one so here let's say
application one
application two application three there
are so many applications
each application which are connected to
a bus let's say this is a spring cloud
bus understand that this is a spring
cloud bus all connected through some
message broker spring cloud bus spring
cloud bus okay each app has a unique ID
or you can say that bus ID and the
format is your application name
application name
colon port number colon some random UU
ID it internally generate like this
and any application which is publishing
an event
let's say app one is publishing an event
to a message broker through spring cloud
bus so spring cloud bus has a condition
hey application one if you are
publishing an event the event is should
be from you only
you should not publish an event on
somebody's else's behalf.
So whoever is publishing an event, it
also pass its ID. Hey, this is my ID, I
am publishing it. So Spring Cloud was
internally
has this whatever the application bus ID
which we have given. If you don't give
it internally, what bus ID it will
compute? application name producer
service port number 8081 and some random
UU ID which you don't even know so it
will generate this okay so it has
application bus ID which it generates
and then whatever we will pass while
publishing an event while publishing an
event through remote we have to pass bus
ID so if you just pass hey producer
service so internal it match hey this
This is what I computed the application
bus ID and this is what you pass it
didn't match. So means you are not the
one you are publishing on somebody
else's behalf. So your pub publishing
event will not even work. It will not
even publish.
So that's why we takes the control of
the bus ID naming. So the bus ID naming
I have given is that hey this is the
application name and hyphen this is the
port number you should use. So now this
is the bus ID it will generate. So
internally when I will publish an event
I will also pass this name only
producer service
port number 8081. So I will pass this
only
and internally it will compute the
spring cloud bus bus ID. Now since I
have overrided it, it will compute this.
So now they both will match and the
publish will work. you will get to know
where it will use but this is very
important. Okay. So we have given one
unique bus ID to this application.
Now
this thing done. So we have added the
dependency. We have added the
application.properties.
Now this is my event which I need to
publish. So you have a publisher which
need to publish an event to a message
broker.
So this is my event.
my remote custom event. Now look
carefully that it extend remote
application event. So earlier when
within a one application we were doing
it, it was application event
but we want spring cloud bus to
intercept this event. So that's why it
need to extend remote application event.
Then only your spring
would be a spring cloud bus would be
able to intercept it. So here this is
the hierarchy. So serializable then
event object then it's uh then
application event extend this event
object. Earlier we were using
application event but if you want a
remote and want spring cloud bus to
intercept it then we have to use this.
It's again a child of application event
only.
Okay. Now here one more difference you
see is that earlier we have only source
like who is publishing it like this
object who is the publisher. Now here we
have origin service destination. Very
important to understand these two.
Origin service destination. Origin
services who is publishing the event
which application not uh this class not
publisher class. We have already covered
this in the source. It is this object.
So it has about this object information
origin services which application is
publishing an event. I told you
hey this is the application which is
publishing an event. So we want to give
this name. If you give any name let's
say producer service internally it will
check hey whatever the name you have
given in the origin service is it
matching with the this application bus
ID. So currently the bus ID is computed
with this. If you don't use this then
bus ID it will compute internally like
this application column port columns and
random UU ID. If these two doesn't match
your publishing will not work.
Okay. So origin service is like which
application is publishing an event.
Destination means this message is intent
to which all listeners. So now let's say
you have a publisher. You publish an
event to listener one, listener two,
listener three, listener four. There are
so many listeners.
Now let's say in destination we can say
that hey this message is intend for
listener one and listener two only.
If you say that like okay doesn't matter
it publish it to all you can put
eststeras or null. So both means that
publish to all
and message is nothing like uh like what
message you want to publish.
Okay. So it just whatever the message we
have it just fill it up. Okay. You can
have more info. This is just like I have
only one field message which I want to
transfer.
So I already told you this very
important part origin service is very
important. Okay.
So we have created our event message
which we have to publish. Now the
publisher which so same very similar to
what we have done in the single
application itself.
So we have a application event publisher
again similarly like one single
application
here I have a method publish I am doing
publish event now here I'm creating my
new remote custom event passing the
source that this is the class object
which is doing the publish this is the
origin service ID which information
about which application is publishing so
here if you see that I carefully sending
the specific bus ID itself. So from the
value from the application.properties
whatever I have configured the same
value I'm passing so that internally the
condition should get true. You can test
like you can pass anything producer
service your publish event will not even
work.
Okay. And then destination I put S like
what whoever are the listeners to this
bus pass it to all and the message.
Okay. very very similar to application
single application.
So now that's publisher is done.
Okay, I just added a controller class
just to initiate the flow. So has a
publish endpoint which is just
initiating the publish this one. This
invoke this method that's all nothing
else.
So your publisher has setup is done.
Your broker setup is done. Rabbit MQ
this is done. Publisher is done.
Okay. Now we are setting up a listener.
In listener also we need this pom
because it need to connect to the rabbit
MQ itself. Okay. So we have a dependency
and in the application.properties we
have provided all the credentials uh so
that it can successfully connect with
the message broker. Okay. And this is
the application name consumer port
number running on 80082 different port
number.
So pom done application.property done.
Now I am adding a listener. So again
everything is same whatever we were
doing in the same single application.
Now we are just like listener is present
into different application.
So event listener. So now here if you
see event listener is same. It is
listening to my remote custom event. So
we can put this class here. this class
right which we have to publish message
we can put it into some common place so
that both publisher and your listener
can access that
remote custom event class or you can
duplicate it like in both the
application you have this class but it
need to be same. So my recommendation
would be you have some common
configuration or common uh you can say
that repo where you have all the common
utility. So here you can say that my
remote custom event class should be
there so that your producer can listen
use this listener can use this class
same common code. So for testing purpose
uh I will share the get link in that one
even in the listener I have this class
copied. So it's currently I'm
duplicating it. So this class present
here also this class present here also.
Okay. But the moto is that event
listener is listening to this event my
remote custom event.
Okay. And just printing it.
That's all. Yeah. And one one last thing
in the listener whatever the uh
application you have here you have to
use at the rate remote application event
scan and you have to provide the base
package like where is this
event remote event present where I have
to look into it. So this package and all
its sub package spring boot will scan.
Why it is required? Because I told you
that this is the flow publisher when
publish
spring cloud bus intercepted it
serialize it. It's a JSON form.
It pass it to the message broker presses
broker. It goes to spring cloud bus as
listener side. It need to des serialize
means JSON to Java object.
Now it need to des serialize right? JSON
to Java object. So while d serializing
it, it need to find out this java
object. Okay. So it need to find out
this my remote custom event.
So where it has to look, it doesn't
know. So that's where with remote
application event scan, we are telling
hey either you can look into this
package or all its sub packages.
So that dialization should work properly
and it able to find this class.
Okay,
that's all.
So our listener is also set up. So our
listener is also set up.
Now let's start publisher and listener.
Okay. And let's start it on our code
also. And let's do that.
So here let me stop it first.
So this is my publisher.
All the code which you are seeing it's
exact the same thing which we have go
through I have also shared into the git
link. So now let's see this I am
starting my
producer app and this is my consumer
app. Let me start my consumer app 2. So
my producer app is running on 8081
here and the consumer app is running on
8082.
So here if you see
producer app uh this one is consumer app
8082 it's up and uh producer app 80081
is also up. So this step we have done.
Now let's invoke the publisher. So here
this is the publish.
Okay. So I am invoking 8081. This is our
publisher running and I am invoking the
message send.
Okay, event publish. Now let's see the
logs.
So consumer. So I'm checking the
consumer app here. If you see received a
remote event in client service hello
world.
So this is what it printed
received the remote event in client
service and this message. So our
listener even though we invoked
the publisher
it successfully
our consumer app able to listen it.
Okay. So hit it again. You will see
received in our consumer app which is
running on 8082 and which we we are
hitting 8081.
Okay. So our setup is working fine. So
this is we have seen it so properly
working fine. So now we understood how
spring cloud bus is working. Now the
real world use case is dynamic refresh.
So now this is where we finished our
previous lecture that
earlier our without spring cloud bus.
This is our setup for the uh
configuration when we manage a central
configuration and we have to dynamically
refresh. This is our setup on config
server. We have to invoke the refresh
and all the 100 services we have to
invoke it. But with the spring cloud bus
this is going to be our setup.
We have config server which now act as a
publisher
which going to publish an event to some
message broker let's say Kafka and from
this all microservices will listen and
their event listener method will get
invoked
okay and here in the config server
instead of normal refresh we have to
invoke actuator bus refresh because bus
refresh it will publish the event we
will see
So first thing first like you have to
see the previous videos otherwise um
because many things we have already set
up the central configuration we have
already set up central uh config servers
this microservices everything is done we
are now just integrating the spring
cloud bus. So if you want a complete
detail for kindly check out the central
configuration and refresh scope dynamic
uh refresh scope okay then after that
this setup would be clear to you.
So here at the config file no change
it's a get repo which holds our
application dot properties. So no change
in that one in config server now see
what change I am doing. So everything we
have previously I am just adding the
AMQP message broker support. Okay. So
that our config server should be able to
connect to the message broker
and in the application.properties I have
added the message broker credentials and
also one more since we have to invoke
bus refresh endpoint so that's why I am
exposing it.
I have already covered that in the
actuator like or in the previous videos.
So you can check it out. That's why I'm
saying it has a prerequis
uh central configuration and refresh
scope two videos.
Okay. So I'm exposing this bus refresh
endpoint
that the minimal change I have done into
the
config server
that's all
the dependency and the property.
Now you might be thinking hey where we
are publishing
where we are doing dotpublish
okay that is within this API when we do
/actuator/bus
refresh right bus refresh internally we
all framework provid us the code for
publishing an event to this message
broker I will show you which class does
that so now publishing is done now the
microservices again dependency
same message broker and in the
application.properties
the credentials so that they can
connect. Okay. Now with this dependency
our spring cloud bus dependency has
come.
So no change in controller whatever we
have previously no change in
configuration properties which we have
to dynamic refresh. That's all. So here
if you see our consumer is also done. We
have just provided the spring cloud bus
dependency and the message broker
details. Now you might be listening here
chance where is at the rate event
listener so that it can listen to the
event whatever it will publish that is
also provided by the framework we don't
have to write it I will also show you
how
so let's see that so start the server
for both config server and order
microserver again let's see this one so
that it would be clear so I'm stopping
this consumer I am now moving to refresh
scope I have everything updated into the
git. Okay. So you can refer the code.
So refresh scope has two modules. One is
server and one is order service. So let
me start the so yeah and one more thing
currently
the central config let's say has this
hello from order tab. So here
so this one the central config hello
from order tab. So let me push this to
this end uh branch refresh scope hyphen
test. So
testing is spring cloud bus.
Okay. So currently
my this div properties is holding this
hello from order dev.
Okay. Now we have to start the server
for our config management. So let's say
let me check its property. It is
currently listening to the main but I
have change on
refresh scope test. Okay. So bus refresh
is there. All endpoint is there. All
looks good. Only this if you have seen
the previous video you know what's the
use of this. It is fetching the
properties from this branch of this
config.
So I am starting the
server. [snorts]
Tomcat is started on 888. So my server
is started. Now I am starting the
different application
micros service.
>> [snorts]
>> 8080.
So we have done this two steps. So our
order application is started on 8080
and our config server is started on 8888
and we have this currently file stored
in our central config. Now let's invoke
the order microservices. So this is the
endpoint we have exposed in order
microservices, right? So /fetch.
So now we are invoking this. So here
/fet. So here when you invoke it what
you are getting hello from order dev.
This is what we have currently. Okay. So
it's properly fetching the property
value. Hello from order dev.
Now update the property in the central
config. Okay. So now what I am doing is
in the central config I am changing it.
This is updated something. This is
updated.
And now I am just committing it
and pushing it again on the branch.
So this is updated.
So I have updated the value from this to
something like this is updated. Okay.
Now let's hit the order API again. So
let's hit the order API again. You will
see that same thing. Hello from order
there. Counter value is two means it we
have hit the second time. We haven't
restarted or anything. So the same
server is running but it you see that it
is not yet updated. It is expected same
old value because we haven't invoked
actuator/bus refresh
bus refresh.
Now let's invoke actuator/bus refresh
endpoint on config server. Okay. So here
if you see config server running on
8888. Now I invoking actuator/bus
refresh
send.
So yes success. Now I have done this
step.
Okay. So I have invoked on config server
888. Now let hit the order API again. So
in order API I haven't invoked the /
refresh endpoint. I'm just again calling
/fetch.
Done. What I'm getting hello from order
dev. This is updated. So now here if you
see the latest config value I am getting
without even I have invoked / refresh
endpoint or slash anything.
So how does it work internally? Because
we have seen that in our config server
we are not doing publish
who is publishing it and in our order we
are not putting any at the rate event
listener who is listening it.
So this is how it works internally.
So on the config server when we call bus
refresh endpoint internally it invokes
this endpoint refresh bus endpoint it is
annotated with like /actuator/bus
refresh. So this endpoint will get
invoked. It's already present into the
framework.
Now here if you see this method will get
invoked and what it is doing it is
publishing an event. Which event?
Refresh remote application event. So
this is the source. This is the bus ID
it is passing. Destination is null. Pass
it to all. Very important. Now here if
you see one question should comes to
your mind. Hey Shri,
it is directly publishing it. So the
setup is like that. So we have a config
in greo.
We have here central
uh config server which fetches from the
config and from this config server our
application fetch order application is
fetched from this config server.
But from this logic what I see is that
when I invoke the bus refresh it
directly do the publish. It directly do
the publish. Hey, so it is uh sorry not
directly to the order server it message
to the broker
message broker and from this message
broker order application. So this is our
spring cloud bus setup.
Hey config server is directly doing
publish
but it hasn't done
refresh itself. It should refresh its
properties first, right? Then only you
should publish it because once you
publish it, the application will catch
it and they will ask, "Hey, config
server give me the latest property." But
config server hasn't uh done the
refreshing yet. Okay? Because what code
I'm seeing is when I invoke /bus
refresh, it is just publishing an event
where it is refreshing itself.
That's a spring cloud bus flow.
Understand that this will become more
clear. So this is what happening
when you invoke /bus refresh
our config server control goes. Okay
this part this class
and it will publish an event publish
and it will goes to the message broker.
What event? Refresh remote application
event. Refresh remote application event.
this it will publish. Now what's the
destination? Null means all application
which are listening to this bus. So in
this bus even the config server is
listening itself. So this message broker
will pass it to all the application
which are listening to this bus. So it
will pass it to config server. It will
pass it to the order microser because
this is also listening to the same bus.
Okay. So it will pass it to the both.
Now in the config server
there is a class already again framework
class refresh listener which has this
method context refresh dotre.
[snorts] So in the refresh listener
there is something called add the rate
event listener present
that will get invoked and that will do
context refresher dot refresh. So it
will fetch the config from the git repo.
Similarly, order microservices
refresh listener which is already
present into the framework class has
this event listener present which does
context refresh. So this cont uh event
listener is listening to this event.
So that will do refresh and it will
fetch the latest config from the config
server.
So you might be thinking that okay now I
understood that the same message is
broadcasted to config server and they
both have a listener already present so
they are already doing the refresh
config okay but what if order
microservices
it received first meanwhile config
server hasn't done the refresh
so generally let's say that assume that
if the event is broadcasted and order
service is going first its listener has
invoked first even though it hasn't done
its refresh completed and when it
refreshes called it will invoke the
config server hey config server give me
the latest data in that scenario since
config server hasn't completed its
refresh yet it make a fresh call to
config fet the latest and then give it
to order
so this is how it's working internally
[snorts]
so I I know it's a lot of information
but if I cover it very high level that
uh without covering how in one
application it work then a custom event
will work in different microservices and
then how it's handled in
uh dynamic refresh. If I cover directly
dynamic refresh and then just say that
okay we just need
this dependency and all done.
So here if you see that all you need is
this dependency
in order service you all you need this
dependency done dynamic refresh done by
spring cloud bus but how is it working
internally that would will keep us keep
on bugging us so I hope this is clear if
you have any doubt let me know we can
discuss further bye